Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated, bulk 1898-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Printed Materials Series, 1903-2008 and undated, bulk 1920s-1990s, (51 boxes)
  - NCM Publications Subseries, 1903-2008 and undated
    - NCM Serials
      - The Whetstone, 1953-1964, (12 folders) (Box 159)
      - The Whetstone, 1965-1977, (13 folders) (Box 160)
      - The Whetstone, 1978-1998, (11 folders) (Box 161)
      - The Whetstone (bound issues), 1943-1950, (1 binder)
      - The Whetstone (bound issues), 1947-1959, (2 binders) (Box 162)
      - The Whetstone (binding removed), 1960-1967, (3 folders) (Box 163)
      - Miscellaneous publications (bound), 1920-1963, (1 binder)
      - The North Carolina Mutual, 1903 Sept., [frame removed] (Box OV38)
        [Some of the materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material, as contents may need to be reproduced before being handled.]
  - Non-NCM Publications Subseries, 1914-2006 and undated
    - NCCU-Related Publications
      Material related to North Carolina Central University, including commencement programs, course guides, an issue of the campus journal Varia, issues of the campus newspaper The Echo, and issues of the faculty newsletter The Faculty Fuzz. Includes oversize material, given at end of grouping.
      - Annual catalogue, 1959-1960 (Box 163)
      - Annual catalogue, 1961-1962
      - Commencement programs, 1959-1964
      - Summer school, 1951
      - Miscellaneous publications, 1960-1992 and undated (
      - Varia journal, 1963
      - Golden Echo, 1960 Jan.; Campus Echo, 1964 Sept. 28; Alumni Bulletin, 1964 Apr. (Box OV35)
      - Faculty and Staff Fuzz, 1963, 1965, (5 issues)
    - Non-NCM Pamphlets and Other Publications
      Various items related to organizations other than North Carolina Mutual. Includes a large collection of material related to African American history; a number of government publications (primarily concerning either the African American population or the state of the economy); files from a 1973 audit of NCM conducted by the firm Ernst and Ernst; brochures and booklets related to health education; and publications produced by the NAACP, the National Urban League, the Southern Regional Council, the National Insurance Association, the Institute of Life Insurance, Ebony, the United Negro College Fund, the National Council of Negro Women, and the Peace Corps, among many others. Arranged in alphabetical order by title or subject, with oversize material at the end.
      - American Heart Association Pamphlets, undated (Box 164)
      - Annual Report, The National Industrial Conference Board, 1967
      - Archives * Records, DC, 2006
      - Atlanta Home Horizons, 1962
      - Bits and Pieces, undated
      - Blacks and Hispanics in the United States, 1979
      - Black history:
        - American Traveler's Guide to Negro History, undated
        - Arno Press, Black Studies Program catalog, 1972
        - The Black Presence in North Carolina exhibition program, 1978
        - Blacks in the Westward Movement, 1975
        - Calendars, 1983-1985
        - Fifty Years of Progress pamphlets, 1950
        - Flags of Famous Black Military Units, 1976
        - Golden Legacy comic book, 1984
        - Merzette coloring books, 1985
        - Negro History Week: A National Celebration, undated
        - Pepper Bird Pathways: African American Heritage, 1995
        - The Pride and the Passion, 1983
      - Black Resource Guide, 1983
      - Blue Cross/Blue Shield of North Carolina annual report, 1994
      - British and Foreign Anti-Slavery Reporter indices, 1840-1846, 1854, 1857-1860 [photocopies]
      - Business training pamphlets, 1948-1983 and undated
      - Can These Bones Live, by R.V. Horton, 1974
      - Choose a Career That Counts, 1959
      - Civil Rights and the South: A Symposium, 1963
      - Conference Board publications, 1966-1969 and undated, (3 folders)
      - Corporate Structure, 1993 (Box 165)
      - Diego Rivera/Mexico tourism material, postcards, undated
      - Durham: A Rare Combinations of Qualities, undated
      - Durham County Almanac, 1925
      - Ebony Publications on Negro Market Potential, 1965 and undated
      - Ernst and Ernst audit, 1973, (3 folders)
      - An Evening with Chuck Davis, program, 1992
      - Falcon Song, World Expo pamphlet, 1992
      - Federal Records Centers folder with various pamphlets, leaflets, undated
      - Government publications:
        - Black Americans: A Chartbook, 1971
        - Causes of Negro Insurance Company Failures, 1937
        - Committee for Economic Development, 1968-1969
        - Department of Labor, 1965-1966
        - Franchise Company Data, 1968
        - General Services Administration occupancy guides, 1963-1965
        - National Negro Health Week, 1928
        - The Negro Woman Worker, 1938
        - Office of Economic Opportunity, 1967
        - The Social and Economic Status of the Black Population in the United States, 1972
        - Third Report of Insurance Companies Owned and Operated by Negroes, 1949
      - Health education, 1994-1998 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 166)
      - History Speaks, 1932
      - Home Insurance Companies, 1933
      - In Loving Memory of Mr. Willie C. Lovett program, 1992
      - Institute of Life Insurance, 1959 and undated
      - The Integration of the Negro into the United States Navy, 1948
      - Joint Center for Political Studies, 1982
      - Life Insurance Facts for Business Women, 1956
      - Martin Luther King and The Montgomery Story, 1956
      - Musings of a Teenager, Lawrence A. Dunmore, 1974
      - National Archives brochures, 2005
      - NAACP publications, 1955-1963, (2 folders)
      - National Council of Negro Women, 1956-1981
      - National Negro Finance Corporation, 1924
      - National Negro Business League Annual Report, 1914
      - National Insurance Association member roster, 2002
      - National Urban League Building for the Future, 1956
      - The Negro and the Depression in North Carolina, 1933
      - Negro History Week, pamphlet, undated, (2 copies)
      - The Newcomen Society, 1958-1960
      - A New Era on Parrish Street pamphlet, circa 2004
      - New Directions, reprint, 1974
      - North American Reassurance Company Forecast for the Seventies, 1962
      - North Carolina AIDS resource directory, 1989
      - North Carolina Black Leadership Caucus fifteenth annual conference, 1991
      - North Carolina Human Relations Council, 1978 (Box 167)
      - Peace Corps publications, 1961 and undated
      - Physical Distribution: Key Points for Presidents, 1967
      - Position paper, Allan P. Sindler, undated
      - Preparing the Annual Report, 1960
      - The Quarterly Earnings Roller Coaster Best's Insurance Review, 1976
      - Race in the News, circa 1950
      - Reading Course in Executive Technique, 1948
      - Register to Vote flier, undated
      - The Road to Justice: Three Major Statements on Civil Rights by President Lyndon B. Johnson, 1965
      - Russian scholarship, 1952-1955 and undated
      - Society of American Archivists Annual Report, 2005
      - Southern Regional Council publications, 1960 and undated
      - Stony the Road We Trod...: a Portrait of Black North Carolinians in Prose and Poetry, 1976 Nov.
      - A Survey of the Years 1898-1899, 1958
      - Tax law information, 1966-1979
      - They Call Him 'Co-operation,' 1943, (2 copies)
      - They Defend Genocide and Cannibalism, remarks of Hon. Claude Pepper, 1965 Feb. 17
      - Thomas Day, Cabinetmaker exhibition program, 1975, (2 copies)
      - Thomas F. Keller Center dedication, 1996
      - Three Peeps and Some Looks, by J. Mason Brewer, 1963 Jun.
      - Toward the Preservation of a Heritage: Inaugural Exhibition of The Howard University Museum, 1979
      - Triad Black Business Expo program, 1994
      - United Negro College Fund, 1958-1964 and undated
      - University of North Carolina commencement, 1967
      - Urinary Analysis by Chemical Examination, 1923
      - Vacuum Freeze-Drying, undated
      - Vocational Training Opportunities in North Carolina, 1963
      - You Can Go Places and See Things in the Life Insurance Business, undated
      - City of Durham master plan report, 1959 (Box OV14)
      - Cosmopolitan Chamber of Commerce report on Chicago, 1965
      - White Rock Baptist Church: A Brief History, undated (Box OV35)
    - Non-NCM Serials
      Several serials not published by NCM, including many issues of The Journal of Negro History and The Pilot, official journal of the National Negro Insurance Association. Arranged in alphabetical order by title, with oversize material at the end.
      - Administrative Management, 1967 Mar. (Box 167)
      - American Magazine, 1948 Dec.
      - American Visions, 1990 June
      - The Atlantic, 1940 May
      - Best's Insurance News, 1943-1967
      - Best's Life Rating Chart, 1928, 1930 (Box 168)
      - Blackbook, 1983
      - Black Business Digest, 1973 May
      - Black Business Ink, 2003 Aug.
      - Black Enterprise, 1974-1993, (4 folders)
      - Black Scholar, 1987 July/Aug./Sept./Oct.
      - Black Southerner Magazine, 1982
      - The Brown American, 1958 Fall
      - Business Automation, 1964 Sept.
      - Business Leader, 1991 Oct.
      - Caravan, 1965 April/May
      - Chief Legal Executive, Winter 2003
      - Concrete Facts, undated (Vol. 12 #2)
      - Concrete Products, 1965 May
      - Council Review, 1985 Apr./May-Sept.
      - The Crisis, 1931-1968, (2 folders)
      - Dollars and Sense, 1983-1986
      - Durham Report, undated
      - Durham YMCA Heartbeats, 1994 Apr.
      - Ebony, 1955 (reprints); 1985; 2005
      - Fortune, 1974 Oct.
      - Humanities, 2006 May/June
      - Input, 1966
      - Inside Track, 1987 Fall
      - The Insurance Examiner, 1939 Mar.
      - The Insurance Leader, 1919-1920 (Box 169)
      - Intercollegiate Digest, 1935 Nov., (2 copies)
      - Jet, 1983-2005
      - The Journal of Negro History, 1962-1996, (8 folders)
      - The Kappa-Alpha-Psi Journal, 1926-1929
      - Local History and Genealogy, 1948
      - The Message, 1951 Sept.
      - The Mouthpiece, 1925 Feb.
      - The Nation, 1952, Sept. 27
      - The National Magazine of Commerce, 1935 Jan.
      - National Negro Digest, circa 1937
      - The Nation-Wide Review, 1928 Sept.
      - The Negro History Bulletin, 1962-1975, (2 of 8 folders)
      - The Negro History Bulletin, 1962-1975, (6 of 8 folders) (Box 170)
      - Negro Progress in North Carolina, 1950-1964, (3 folders)
      - The Negro Worker, 1944 July
      - The New York Stock Exchange Magazine, 2005 May/June
      - Opportunity, 1923-1935
      - Pageant, 1963 July
      - The Pilot, 1951-1954, (8 folders)
      - The Pilot, 1955-1965, (17 folders) (Box 171)
      - The Pilot, 1966-1978, (13 folders) (Box 172)
      - Probe, 1961 April
      - The Quarterly Journal, 1940 October
      - The Radiator, 1922-1923, (4 folders)
      - The Saturday Evening Post, 1945 Mar. 27
      - Sepia, 1983 July
      - Survey Graphic, 1942 Nov.
      - Tar Heel Junior Historian, African American Life Edition, 1995 Fall
      - The Trumpet of Conscience, undated (Vol. 1, No. 2)
      - The Underwriters' Forum, 1947 Jan.-May
      - The Wayfarer, 1965 Fall
      - Weekly News Review Digest and Best's Insurance News, 1924-1940
        Carries extensive handwritten annotations and lists.
      - The Messenger, 1927 Mar. (Box OV9)
      - The Saturday Evening Post, 1943 Mar. 27 (Box OV14)
      - Sentinel, 1983 Apr. 14
      - Hotline and Unity News, 1963-1983 (Box OV36)
      - The Triangle Tribune, 1998 Oct. 11, (NC Mutual 100th anniversary edition)
      - Tribune supplement, 1966, and The Durham Morning Herald, 1973 Nov. 4
      - Chicago Daily Defender, 1965 Dec. 8-9
      - Photocopy of The Durham Sun, 1921 Dec. 31, and Campus Echo, 1957 Feb. 28
      - The Insurance Field, 1926 Aug. 6
      - Ebony, 1955 Sept.; 1959 Mar. (reprints) (Box OV37)
      - Ebony, 1963 May; 1966 June; 1967 Mar.-Apr.; 1969 May; 1971 Mar; 1973 Aug.-Sept., Dec., (5 folders)
      - The Little Voice, 1927 July 9 (Box OV38)
      - The Carolina Times, 1966 Mar. 5, 19, 26, Apr. 9; 1968 Dec. 14; 1994 Sept. 24
      - The Carolinian, 1983 Feb. 17
      - Double Ought, 1999 Nov. - 2000 Oct.
      - Durham Morning Herald, 1966 Mar. 12, Apr. 3; 1968 May 5; 1981 Apr. 26
      - The Durham News Journal, 1966 Mar. 31
      - The Durham Sun, 1966 Mar. 31
      - The Macon Courier, 1983 Feb. 15
      - The News and Observer, 1992 June 17
      - The Philadelphia Tribune, 1983 Feb. 8
      - The Wall Street Journal, 1994 Sept. 27
  - Periodical Clippings Subseries, 1906-1996 and undated
    Contains groups of clippings, mostly assembled by the Public Relations Department, from mainstream national and local newspapers, university newspapers, and African American publications. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - Civil rights, 1947-1960, (3 folders) (Box 173)
    - League of Women Voters, 1950-1953
    - North Carolina newspapers, 2005
    - NCM, 1960-1966, 1991, (2 folders)
    - Richmond, Tyronza, 1994
    - Spaulding, C.C., undated
    - Tillotson College, undated
    - Tougaloo Southern Christian College, 1945-1956
    - Town Hall world tours, 1949-1953
    - Toure, Sekou, 1959-1961
    - Tuskegee Institute, AL, 1949-1958
    - Various topics, 1955-1968, 1984, (3 folders)
    - Washington, Booker T., 1946-1960
    - Washington, George, 1953
    - Watchtower Life Insurance Company, Houston TX, 1939
    - Weaver, Robert C., 1961-1962
    - Wilberforce University, OH, 1949-1956
    - Wiley College, TX, 1958
    - William Penn Business School, 1951
    - Williamsburg VA, 1962
    - Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1935-1957
    - Winston-Salem Teachers' College, 1961
    - Wit and humor (wise sayings), 1948-1955, (2 folders) (Box 174)
    - Women of the Week and Year, 1949-1957
    - Wright, Richard, 1961
    - WTCU, 1949-1953
    - Xavier University, 1949-1952
    - Y-Teens, 1955
    - Ye Towne on Queen Anne's Creek, 1962
    - YMCA, 1949-1957
    - YWCA, 1950-1958
    - Zeta Phi Beta sorority, 1950-1953
    - Various topics, oversize clippings, 1955-1967 (Box OV4)
      [Some of the materials in this box are fragile and in need of preservation. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material, as contents may require photocopying before being handled.]
    - Various topics, oversize clippings, 1936, 1953, 1964, 1967, 1984 (Box OV9)
    - Various topics, 1967, 1982, 2006 (Box OV23)
    - Civil rights, The Picture News, 1947 Nov. 2 (Box OV35)
    - Various topics, 1984, 1991-1994, (3 folders)
    - C.C. Spaulding, 1942 Dec. 12
    - NCM oversize clippings, 1921, 1926 (Box OV39)
    - Laminated NCM clippings, 1906, 1921, 1966, 1988
    - Kennedy, Jr., W.J., 1952-1958
    - Wheeler, J.L. funeral notices, 1957 Apr. 22
    - Lawsuit and annual meeting, 1972-1973
    - Various topics, 1943-1966, (3 folders)
    - Various topics, 1983-1996, (5 folders)
- Recordings Series, 1943-circa 1970s, (24 boxes and film cans)
  Series houses sound and moving image recordings spanning many decades and documenting milestones in North Carolina Mutual History. Formats include audiocassettes, audio tape reels, film reels, and videocassettes.
  Audiocassettes are few in number and include a set of home-study tapes on insurance practices.
  Subjects of films include a history of North Carolina Mutual; the history of "Black Wall Street" in Durham; the groundbreaking and dedication ceremonies for the current headquarters building on Chapel Hill Street in Durham; and advertisements and broadcasts about NC Mutual products and services. Titles of films listed have been taken from original canister or box labels. Many of these films were copied in digital format to DVD, around 2002 (see listings of digitized moving images in Digital Material Series).
  [Original audiovisual recordings are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection. Slated for further preservation and identification work.]
  - Audio Recordings Subseries, 1987
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
    - HS 328, Investments - audio cassette for home study created by Insurance Achievement, Inc., 1987, (5 cassettes) (Box 175)
    - "The Great Transition," 1977, (3 cassettes)
    - Audio tape reels, (22 reels) (Box 175-A)
      Primarily consists of radio commercials. 3", 4", and 5" reels.
    - Unidentified audio tape reels, (3 reels) (Box 175-B)
      Unlabeled, 8" reels.
    - Adventures in Negro History (Box 175-C)
      Set of commercially produced record albums (LPs) with booklet.
    - The Saxton Show, 1962 Feb. 15
      Radio show featuring guests Asa Spaulding and H.J. Clement, 10.5" reel.
  - Films Subseries, 1948-1976 and undated
    Series of NCM-produced films and advertising spots, including a history of NCM created in 1948. Film footage is approximate. All but FILM 17 are reels of film; FILM 17 is an archival box housing multiple films.
    - Black Ambassador, Home and Abroad, circa 1976, (2550 feet) (Film-reel 1)
      "Shipped to WRAL-TV...6/25/76." Memorex video tape, 2".
    - Hi band dub N.C. Mutual Founders' Day 29:19, 1970 October 24, (3200 feet) (Film-reel 2)
      RCA video tape, 2".
    - Dubs of NC Mutual Founders Day, undated, (3200 feet) (Film-reel 3)
      RCA, video tape, 2".
    - WTTW #47325 Spaulding Spots, circa 1964 (Film-reel 4)
      WTTW in Chicago. Three small reels inside 11.5" can.
    - Success Story, undated (Film-reel 5)
      "Missing most of title."
    - NC Mutual, 1966, (747 feet) (Film-reel 6)
      Charles Crone Agency. Black and white 16mm film.
    - Dedication Ceremony, 1966, (1200 feet) (Film-reel 7)
      16mm film.
    - Groundbreaking, circa 1965, (1200 feet) (Film-reel 8)
      "Film and video tape division WTTW Chicago."
    - Success Story 1948 800 in. full reel, undated, (800 feet?) (Film-reel 9)
      16 mm film.
    - NC Mutual Ads #1-4, Dangerfield, undated (Film-reel 10)
      Container houses 3.5" reel with one film; and one 4.75" reel with four films on it, according to labels. 16mm format.
    - NC Mutual, Charles Crone Assoc., undated, (500 feet) (Film-reel 11)
    - NCM Dedication Ceremonies, 1966, (700 feet) (Film-reel 12)
    - NC Mutual 'Success Story,' undated, (500 feet) (Film-reel 13)
    - NC Mutual, circa 1966, (100 feet, 2 reels) (Film-reel 14)
      "Humphrey 1966." WTTW kine negative original.
    - NC Mutual, 1966 April 15, (810 feet) (Film-reel 15)
      WTTW kine negative original. Also on can: "Humphrey neg 1966." 16mm, sound.
    - The Quiet Road to Success, VTR #1, 29:30, WRAL-TV 5, Raleigh (Film-reel 16)
    - Tribute to Martin Luther King, January 14, 1972, 2:37: Producer: Clayton Weaver (Box FILM 17)
    - North Carolina Mutual, Jogger, 0:30, 28 May '81: Brand Edmonds Packett, WDBJ-TV7, Roanoke
    - NC Mutual Insurance, Jogger, 0:30, 10-17-80: WPTF-TV28
    - NC Mutual, NCMU-0130, 0:30, dub 9/3/81: WRAL-TV5, Raleigh
    - The Achiever, 0:30 commercial spot, color, (7 copies)
    - Success Story, b/w, mailed 1959 Oct. 12, (includes small sections that were removed from the enclosed film)
      [This film is in need of preservation. Please contact a reference archivist to use this material, as contents should be treated before being handled.]
    - (Box FILM 18)
    - Film reels, (19 film reels) (Box FILM 19)
      primarily consists of television commercials on 16 mm film.
  - Videocassettes, 1992-1999 and undated
    Titles and dates are taken from original container labeling. Total running time (TRT) given when possible. Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - Antique Truck, [U-Matic, TRT :30] (Box 175A)
    - Community Mental Health and Health Care Reform, with Dr. Fred McCall Perez, a member of President Clinton's Health Care Task Force, 1990s, [VHS, TRT :30] (Box 176)
    - NIA 1997 Atlanta, Howard Catching and Coretta Scott King, [VHS]
    - NIA 1997 Awards Banquet, [VHS]
    - NIA 1997 President's Banquet, J. Lowery, [VHS]
    - 95 Years of Sales and Service, 1993, [VHS
    - NCM Centennial Celebration Documentary, 1999, [VHS]
    - NCM Christmas, 1992, [VHS]
    - NCM Employee Forum, 1999, [VHS]
    - NCM: The First 100 Years, ca. 1999, [VHS]
    - NCM 94th Founders Day Program, 1992, [VHS]
- Scrapbooks Series, 1912-1975, (6 boxes)
  Varying in size and condition, these scrapbooks commemorate the history of North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance through clippings, photographs, memos, programs, and other items. Also found in the photographic material section in the Oversize Material Series are photo albums that also commemorate company personnel, conferences and other events, and milestones.
  [Scrapbooks are fragile; some are slated for further preservation treatment. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this material.]
  - Scrapbook 1, 1966 (Box OV40)
    Commemorating the dedication of new home office building, this scrapbook chiefly contains many pages of congratulatory messages in the form of letters and telegrams, many from notable officials, politicians, and businessmen.
  - Scrapbook 2, 1975 (Box OV41)
    History of NC Mutual from its beginnings to the 1970s. Almost completely made up of cut-outs from the company publication Whetstone.
  - Scrapbook 3, 1961-1967 (Box OV42)
    Contains newspaper clippings of NCM advertisements, along with a photograph, clippings of competitor's ads, and an event program. Approximately 25" x 17".
  - Scrapbook 4, 1920-1939 (Box OV43)
    Eighteen-page portfolio (approximately 13" x 16") belonging to calligrapher and illustrator Walter W. Micheaux. Micheaux was recognized as an expert penman and, after moving from South Carolina. in 1916, illustrated and hand-lettered the insurance policies, publicity, logos, and other material for NCM for over 20 years. Scrapbook contains many original examples of his work, as well as a 1928 clipping about him (with photo), and a small photo of him as an older man.
    [Extremely fragile. Slated for conservation treatment. Please consult with a reference archivist before using.]
  - Scrapbook 5, 1912, 1943-1963, 1972 and undated (Box OV47)
    The majority of the contents of this scrapbook are dedicated to the launching of the S.S. Merrick in honor of John Merrick on July 11, 1943. Also includes a specially-bound edition of the Whetstone edition honoring NCM's 50th anniversary, as well as various newspaper clippings relating to individuals and other entities connected to NCM. Other items laid in to the scrapbook are copies of a letter and photo from President John F. Kennedy, a 1946 Whetstone honoring John Merrick, and an unidentified Atlantic City vacation photograph of NC Mutual staff, circa 1940s.
  - Scrapbook 6, 1936-1941 (Box 177)
    Scrapbook of newspaper clippings belonging to J.L. Wheeler, NCM Agency Director of the Southern Region.
- Social Groups and Events Series, 1922-1992 and undated, (1 box)
  Files relate to social clubs and events for North Carolina Mutual employees. The groups that are chronicled in these files include the NCM Glee Club and the Tuesday Morning Study Group, a self-improvement group composed chiefly of the wives of NCM administrators that met to read about and discuss political, social and cultural topics of the day. Materials on the latter make up the majority of these items.
  - Greetings, Announcements, and Ads, 1924-1927 (Box 178)
  - Tuesday Morning Study Club